Wyler, Julius; Papers ger102
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Julius V. Wyler Papers
1903-1959
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger102
7 cubic ft.
The Julius V. Wyler Papers consist of correspondence, publications by Wyler and other economists (in German and in English), and course and lecture notes from his years of teaching at the New School for Social Research in New York.
Biographical Sketch
Julius Wyler, born August 9, 1891 in Basel, Switzerland, immigrated to the United States in 1941, arriving in New York City on the day of his fiftieth birthday. A month later, he joined the Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research where he lectured for the next fifteen years on topics in statistics, economic research, national income, world economy, and United States industrial development.
In addition to lecturing at the New School for Social Research, Wyler also participated in the Council of Research of the Institute of World Affairs of the New School from 1944 to 1951. He also worked with the Office of Strategic Services in 1941-1942 on a project dealing with the gross national product of nine belligerent countries, and spent another year 1943-1944 working at the National Bureau of Economic Research on a comprehensive survey of the national incomes of over thirty countries.
Before immigrating to the United States, Wyler served for twenty-five years in the Federal Statistical Office (Eidgenössische Statistische Amt) in Berne, Switzerland, working first as a statistical clerk and later promoted to Assistant Director of the Office. During his years at the Statistical Office, he reorganized and edited the Statistical Yearbook of Switzerland, headed the division of Vital Statistics, and was commissioned to head a study of the reorganization of the entire governmental statistics of Switzerland. He conducted numerous studies, many of which were published under the name of the Federal Statistical Office. Wyler also served as a guest lecturer to the Economic Division of the Faculty of Law at the University of Berne, giving classes on statistics, population, business cycles and national income. During the three years immediately preceding his emigration to the U.S., Wyler was granted a Rockefeller Research Fellowship for a study of the estimates of the balance of payments in the United States and Canada, also allowing him several months of study in the United States.
Julius Wyler died in 1959 in Forest Hills, New York, survived by his wife and one daughter, Eva.
Chronology of Events
1891 August 9 born in Basel, Switzerland.
1911-1915 Studied economics, philosophy and modern history at the universities of Basel, Bonn, Leipzig and Paris
1916 Awarded the degree of Doctor of Philosophy from the University of Basel, Switzerland, after completion of his doctoral thesis on Die Tontinen in Frankreich.
1916 August joined the Federal Statistical Office (Eidgenössische Statistische Amt) in Berne, Switzerland.
1916-1941 Worked in the Eidgenössische Statistische Amt, first as a statistical clerk, and finally promoted to Assistant Director; also lectured as part of the economic division of the Faculty of Law at the University of Berne on statistics, population, business cycles and national income.
1917 Reorganized the Statistical Yearbook of Switzerland, of which he was editor for 24 years.
1921 Took over the division of Vital Statistics, working closely with medical advisers in the field of mortality statistics.
1928 Commissioned to head a study of the reorganization of the entire governmental statistics of Switzerland.
1929 Delegate of the Swiss Government at the International Conference in Paris on the classification of the causes of death.
1935-1936 Involved in a study dealing with the estimation of the Swiss balance of payments.
1938-1941 Granted a Rockefeller Research Fellowship for a study of the estimates of the balance of payments in the United States and Canada.
1941 Emigrated to the United States; arrived on August 9.
1941-1956 Member of the Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research.
1941-1942 November 1941 - July 1942, worked with the Economic Financial and Transit Department of the League of Nations in Princeton, New Jersey on studies in international trade.
1943-1944 Collaboration with Professor Paul Studenski under the auspices of the National Bureau of Economic Research in the Compendium of National Income Estimates on a comprehensive survey of the national incomes of over thirty countries.
1944 Received an assignment from the Office of Strategic Services, dealing with the gross national product of nine belligerent countries.
1948 Appointed to Full Professor of the Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research.
1956 Retirement from the New School for Social Research.
1959 Died in Forest Hills, New York.
Scope and Contents
The Julius V. Wyler Papers consist of correspondence, publications by Wyler and other economists (in German and in English), and course and lecture notes from his years of teaching at the New School for Social Research in New York.
The collection has been divided into six series: 1) Biographical materials; 2) Correspondence files, 1940-1959; 3) Published and unpublished writings by Julius Wyler, 1916-1959; 4) Publications by others; 5) Pamphlets; and 6) Course and research notes and materials.
The largest part of the collection consists of Wyler's predominately handwritten lecture and course notes, which include several full-length texts of textbooks for courses he taught at the New School for Social Research, including Applied Statistics, Elementary General Statistics, National Income, and The Structure of the World Economy. Wyler's published writings include those written for the Federal Statistical Office (Eidgenössische Statistische Amt) in Berne, Switzerland, from 1916-1941, as well as publications in English and German from his years in the United States.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Biographical Materials
Series 2: Correspondence Files, 1940-1959
Series 3: Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wyler, 1916-1959
Series 4: Publications by Others
Series 5: Pamphlets
Series 6: Course and research notes and materials
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Eva Wyler, daughter of Julius Wyler, in July 1980.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Economics; Economics -- Study and teaching.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees.; Wyler, Julius V., 1892-1959.; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997)
- Biographical Materials, Undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains a brief biographical statement by Wyler, copies of his publication lists, and one brief newspaper article on the event of his 65th birthday.
  - Curriculum vitae, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 1)
  - Lists of publications, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 2)
  - Clipping, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 3)
- Correspondence Files, 1940-1959; 2; 98 file folders
  This series contains correspondence with administrators and colleagues at the New School for Social Research, including Alvin Johnson, Hans Neisser, Hans Simons, Hans Staudinger, as well as correspondence dealing with publications and with other scholars, including Naum Jasny, Felix Kaufmann, Simon Kuznets, and Paul Studenski.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Abelin, J., 1958 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 4)
  - Ackerman, George F. (EcoStat Research), 1949 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 5)
  - Amonn, A., 1958 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 6)
  - Baiman, Jerome, 1958; typescript (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 7)
  - Baran, Paul A., 1951 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 8)
  - Bergson, Abram, 1951; 1953 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 9)
  - Biske, Käthe, 1958 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 10)
  - Block, Herbert, 1953-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 11)
  - Bode, Karl, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 12)
  - Braunschweig, Max, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 13)
  - Brokow, C. Miriam (Princeton University Press), 1959 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 14)
  - Bruschweiler, Carl, 1946-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 15)
  - Buber, Martin, Undated (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 16)
  - Cohrssen, Hans R. L., 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 17)
  - Colm, Gerhard, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 18)
  - Constantacatos, H. E., 1955 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 19)
  - Copeland, Morris A., 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 20)
  - Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, 1941-1951 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 21)
  - Derksen, J. B., 1945-1951 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 22)
  - Deyrup, Felicia J., 1950 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 23)
  - Doblin, Ernest M., 1943; 1946 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 24)
  - Dunn, Halbert L., 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 25)
  - The Econometric Society (Alfred Cowles), 1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 26)
  - Giannone, Antonio, 1953-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 27)
  - González Gorrondona, J. (Banco Central de Venezuela), 1956-1958 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 28)
  - Grob-Schmidt, Dora, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 29)
  - Grossmann, Eugen, 1941; 1947 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 30)
  - Gruenbaum, A. Ludwig, 1949 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 31)
  - Gumbel, Emil J., 1941; 1959 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 32)
  - Haberler, Gottfried, 1941-1944 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 33)
  - Heimann, Eduard, 1946-1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 34)
  - Hilgerdt, F., 1843 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 35)
  - Hirsch, Julius, 1948 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 36)
  - Hovde, Bryn J., 1946; 1948 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 37)
  - Hula, Erich, 1941; 1946 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 38)
  - Imler, Paul, Undated (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 39)
  - Jasny, Naum, 1947-1955 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 40)
  - Jaszi, George, 1945; 1951 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 41)
  - Johnson, Alvin, 1941-1955 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 42)
  - Journal of Political Economy, 1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 43)
  - Kafka, Fritz, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 44)
  - Kallen, Horace M., 1946 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 45)
  - Kapp, K. William (Ted), 1946-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 46)
  - Kaufmann, Felix, 1941-1946 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 47)
  - Kern, Leo, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 48)
  - Kirk, Dudley, 1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 49)
  - Klein, L. R., 1945 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 50)
  - Kohn, Hans, 1943 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 51)
  - Koller, A., 1954-1955 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 52)
  - Konvitz, Milton R., 1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 53)
  - Kracauer, Friedel & Lili, 1950; 1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 54)
  - Kullmann, Eugen, 1949 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 55)
    (subject: Felix Kaufmann).
  - Kuznets, Simon, 1941-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 56)
  - Landmann, Edith, 1948 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 57)
  - Legation of Switzerland, 1941-1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 58)
  - Loveday, A., 1941-1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 59)
  - Lowe, Adolph, 1941; 1950-1953 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 60)
  - MacGregor, Donald, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 61)
  - Marschak, Jacob, 1941-1944 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 62)
  - Mayer, Carl, 1948 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 63)
  - Meier, E., 1955; 1957 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 64)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1942; 1953 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 65)
  - Neisser, Hans, 1947-1958 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 66)
  - New School for Social Research, 1940 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 67)
    (appointment letter).
  - Notestein, Frank W. (Princeton University), 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 68)
  - Pan American Sanitary Bureau, 1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 69)
  - Richter, J. H., 1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 70)
  - Riefler, Winfield W., 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 71)
  - Rosenberg, A. (League of Nations), 1941; 1945 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 72)
  - Sachs, Alexander, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 73)
  - Salomon, Albert, 1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 74)
  - Schneider, Salome, 1942 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 75)
  - Schwarzmann, Rudolf, 1953; 1957 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 76)
  - Simons, Hans, 1942-1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 77)
  - Social Research, 1943-1944; 1952 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 78)
  - Solow, Herbert, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 79)
  - Sommer, Louise, 1950; 1953 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 80)
  - Speier, Hans, 1948 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 81)
  - Staudinger, Else, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 82)
  - Staudinger, Hans, 1943-1959 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 83)
  - Stolper, Wolfgang, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 84)
  - Strauss, Leo, 1943-1946 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 85)
  - Studenski, Paul, 1942-1955 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 86)
  - Tagliacozzo, Giorgio, 1944; 1949 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 87)
  - Thomas, Alfred F., 1944 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 88)
  - Triebow, 1957 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 89)
  - von Mises, [Ludwig], 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 90)
  - Wagner, Valentin F., 1947-1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 91)
  - Weiller, Jean-S, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 92)
  - Weiss, Francis Joseph, 1948 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 93)
  - Wertheimer, Franz, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 94)
  - Wunderlich, Frieda, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 95)
  - Wyler, Alfred, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 96)
  - "Baby Boom" correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 97)
  - "Soviet Union -- National Budget" correspondence with the Handwörterbuch der Sozialwissenschaften, 1952-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 98)
  - "Soviet Union -- National Budget" -- general correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 99)
  - Recommendations, 1944; 1947; 1957 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 100)
  - Miscellaneous & unidentified, 1941-1957 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 101)
- Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wyler, 1916-1959; 3; 73 file folders
  This series contains many of the published writings of Wyler, both from his years at the Federal Statistical Office (Eidgenössische Statistische Amt) in Switzlerand (in German, 1916-1940), as well as from his years in the United States (in English and in German, 1941-1959). This series also contains materials from the Council of Research of the Institute of World Affairs of the New School for Social Research and includes typescripts by Wyler and and other participants, 1944-1951. Also included in this section are course outlines and reading lists from courses taught by Wyler at the New School.
  Box 2, Folders 18-34: Papers prepared under the auspices of the Council of Research of the Institute of World Affairs of the New School for Social Research, by Julius Wyler and others, 1944-1951.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - General Writings, 1916-1944; 3.1
    - Die Tontinen in Frankreich, 1916; bound copy (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 102)
      Wyler's dissertation.
    - Wyler's articles published in the Zeitschrift für schweizerische Statistik & Volkswirtschaft, 1916-1918; bound copy (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 103)
    - Wyler's articles published in the Zeitschrift für schweizerische Statistik & Volkswirtschaft, 1919-1920; bound copy (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 104)
    - Die Demographie der Ausländer in der Schweiz, 1921 (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 105)
    - Wyler's articles published in the Zeitschrift für schweizerische Statistik & Volkswirtschaft, 1921-1922; bound copy (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 106)
    - Die schweizerische Bevölkerung unter dem Einflusse des Weltkrieges, 1922 (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 107)
    - Das Übervölkerungsproblem der Schweiz, 1923 (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 108)
    - Das schweizerische Volkseinkommen im Jahre 1924, 1927 (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 109)
    - "Die Grenznutzenlehre und die Werttheorie Othmar Spanns", 1928; reprint (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 110)
    - "Mathmatisch-statistischer Nachweis der langen Welle der Arbeitslosigkeit in der Nachkriegszeit" (with Manuel Saitzew), 1930; reprint (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 111)
    - "Die 'subjektive' und die 'objektive' Seite der Grenznutzentheorie", 1931; reprint (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 112)
    - "Geschichte der Sterbetafeln", Undated; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 113)
    - "Darstellung und statistische Erfassung der Kapitalposten (Bestand, Erträge, Bewegung) in der Zahlungsbilanz", 1939; bound typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 114)
    - "Bemerkungen zum Bericht von Dr. J. Rosenwasser über die Stellung der Schweiz als Gläubiger- und Schuldnerland", 1939; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 115)
    - Die Bevölkerung der Schweiz: Gebürtigkeit und Heimat, 1939 (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 116)
    - "Zahlungsbilanz und Inflation" in Bericht über die Massnahmen zur Inflationsverhütung in der Schweiz, 1940 (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 117)
    - "Die schweizerische Volkseinkommen", 1941; reprint (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 118)
    - Review of Simon Kuznets National Income and Its Composition, 1919-1938. Vol. I and II, 1942 December (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 119)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 120)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 1. United Kingdom", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 121)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 2. Canada", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 122)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 3. Australia", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 123)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 4. New Zealand", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 124)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 5. South Africa", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 125)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 6. Soviet Russia", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 126)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 7. Germany", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 127)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944. 8. Japan", 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 128)
    - "The Economic War Effort of the Allied Nations and the Axis Powers 1938 to 1944". Notes, tables, 1944 September; typescript (Box 1 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 129)
    - "National Income, Economic Reality, Economic Theory", ca. 1946-1947; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 1)
    - "The National Income of Soviet Russia", 1946 December; reprint (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 2)
    - "National Income Estimates of Soviet Russia -- their Distinguishing Characteristics and Problems" (with Paul Studenski), 1947 May; Reprints, typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 3)
    - "Die neueste Entwicklung der Volkseinkommensschätzungen", 1948; reprint (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 4)
    - "Die Schätzungen des sowjetrussischen Volkseinkommens", 1951; Reprints, typescripts (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 5)
    - "The Share of Capital Investment in the Soviet National Expenditure", 1952; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 6)
    - Review of Kurt B. Mayer The Population of Switzerland, 1952; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 7)
    - "Working Capital and Output". Reprints, 1953 Spring (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 8)
    - "The Formation of the Swiss Democracy". Reprints, 1953 Summer (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 9)
    - "Nationalbudget". Reprints, 1954 February (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 10)
    - "The Role of Government Product in National Income". Reprints, 1959 Summer (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 11)
    - Review of Wilson H. Grabill, Clyde V. Kiser, Pascal K. Whelpton The Fertility of American Women, 1959 Autumn; Reprints, typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 12)
    - "The Baby Boom Puzzle". Introduction, bibliography, 1959; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 13)
    - "The Baby Boom Puzzle. Chapter One: Legitimate Fertility", 1959; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 14)
    - "The Baby Boom Puzzle. Chapter Two: Family Size (Cohort Fertility)", 1959; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 15)
    - "The Baby Boom Puzzle. Chapter Three: The Structure of the Families by the Number of Children (Parity Distribution)", 1959; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 16)
    - "The Baby Boom Puzzle. Conclusions: Towards an Explanation of the Baby Boom", 1959; typescript (Box 2 (3-Published and Unpublished Writings by Julius V. Wy), Folder 17)